<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A judgment &amp; condemnation of the Fifth-Monarchy-men, their late insurrection. Also, how far the guilt of that fact may justly be imputed to those that are commonly distinguished by the names of Independants, Presbyterians, Anabaptists and Quakers. Set forth in a letter to a friend. . By a moderate gentleman.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 16 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87427</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J1171</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1055_13</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208005</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867012</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867012</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119302</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87427)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119302)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 156:E1055[13])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A judgment &amp; condemnation of the Fifth-Monarchy-men, their late insurrection. Also, how far the guilt of that fact may justly be imputed to those that are commonly distinguished by the names of Independants, Presbyterians, Anabaptists and Quakers. Set forth in a letter to a friend. . By a moderate gentleman.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 9, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year M DC LXI. [1661]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan 17".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fifth Monarchy Men --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119302:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 35 -->
            <p>A JUDGMENT &amp; CONDEMNATION Of the Fifth-Monarchy-Men, THEIR Late Inſurrection.</p>
            <p>ALSO, How far the Guilt of that Fact may juſtly be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to Thoſe that are commonly diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed by the Names of <hi>Independents, Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians, Anabaptiſts</hi> and <hi>Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Set forth in a <hi>LETTER</hi> to a Friend.</p>
            <p>By a Moderate GENTLEMAM.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Let him that thinketh he ſtandeth, take heed leſt he fall.<lb/>
The Throne ſhall be eſtabliſhed by Righteouſneſs.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed in the Year MDCLXI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:119302:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 36 -->
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119302:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 36 -->
            <head>A Judgement and Condemnation Of the <hi>Fifth-Monarchy-Men,</hi> THEIR Late Inſurrection.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>VAnity of vanities, ſaith the Preacher, vanity of vanities, All is vanity:</hi> and ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Man is like to vanity; his dayes are as a ſhadow that paſſeth away.</hi> But <hi>man that is born of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is</hi> not onely <hi>of few days,</hi> as <hi>Job</hi> ſaith, but alſo <hi>full of trouble.</hi> Who is able to reckon up the manifold Calamities, Evils and Miſeries that poor man doth neceſſarily yeild to? yea, even wiſe men as well as fools; good men as well as evil. But how infinite and hideous are thoſe evils that men expoſe themſelves to through the Prevalencie of their own luſts and appetites, which <hi>when they have once conceiv'd and brought forth ſin, do afterward bring forth death!</hi> And beſides theſe, there is yet another ſort of evils which
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119302:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 37 -->
helps to fill up the meaſure of mans miſery, and which befall him as he is a man (for <hi>Humanum eſt errare</hi>) and that is error, of the miſtake of the underſtanding fa<gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lty, in iudging Truth to be falſhood, or Falſhood Truth. The firſt ſort of <gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is common to moſt <gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>. Theſe <gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is in the fulleſt ſence peculiar to bad men, who are habituated to the following of the allurements of the fleſh, rather then the dictates of reaſon and true religion. But good men are not wholly free from the miſchiefs that attend their negligence and remiſneſs in admitting even preſumptuous ſins. But the third ſort of evils that proceed from Ignorance, both wel-minded and ill-minded men are ſubject to, with this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, that the goodneſs and compaſſion of the Almighty will not ſuffer the well-minded to erre damnably and finally. An Example of one ſinning damnably through Ignorance, we have in the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> who ſaith of himſelf, that he was a Blaſphemer, <hi>a perſecutor of the Church, and injurious; but he obtained mercy, becauſe he did it ignorantly,</hi> in unbeliefe. And whoſe heart, that hath yet any humane blood, doth not bleed within him, to behold the moſt deplorable Effects of the damnable ignorance of ſome men in this our day, who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing themſelves to be ſervants and ſubjects of Jeſus, who is Prince of peace, do notwithſtanding through miſtaken zeal, expoſe and deſtroy both themſelves and others, in breaking peace, and making war! Thus though the Goſpel is <hi>a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of peace,</hi> yet accidentally <hi>it brings not peace on earth, but a ſword;</hi> and that which makes it moſt ſad, is this, that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury is done not by the world againſt the profeſſors of Chriſt (as it was wont to be) but by thoſe miſerable profeſſors againſt the world, yea even their brethren.</p>
            <p>The Moraliſts, and Divines too, divide ignorance into two kinds; vincible and invincible ignorance: invincible is that, when the Truth lies ſo deeply hid, and is ſo ſubtle and intri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, or at leaſt our means of information, or Capacities are ſo ſlender and weak; and on the contrary the arguments for Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror ſo plauſible, and our education and converſe ſo prevalent,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119302:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 37 -->
that it is either utterly impoſſible, or very near an impoſſibli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, for ſuch men to find out the truth. In this caſe, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as it comes neerer to, or is more remote from abſolute impoſſibility, it doth more or leſs excuſe. But where there are ſufficient means of knowledge, a competent capacity, the truth is obvious, and no greater impediments then ſuch as good men do commonly overcome in this caſe, the ignorance is vincible: and if it be a matter of neceſſary concernment, there muſt needs be ſome ſecret luſt or vice, or notable negligence in men, that hinders them from the knowledge of the Truth in that particular; and ſo they are found defaulty in their wills, and demeriting puniſhment more or leſs, according to the degree of their voluntary malignity.</p>
            <p>Theſe things premis'd and conſider'd, the horrid facts, with the great pretenſions of the Fifth-Monarchy-Men, aforemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, to the Reign of Chriſt, proclaiming <hi>Jeſus</hi> King, even with deſpair of life, and the violent impulſe they appear to have had to this ſtrange worke, as alſo their dayly converſe with holy Scriptures, frequent watchings, faſtings and prayers, it will eaſily appear that what they have done, they have ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantly done, and as ſometime the Jews, yea, <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, having <hi>a Zeal of God, but not according to knowledge:</hi> But if we weigh on the other hand, the means they have had of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the truth in this point, the many grave men and elaborate Treatiſes of a contrary judgement, with which they might and ought to have convers'd; the Emergent Acts of Divine Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment amongſt us, croſſing their imaginations, and fruſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their expectations; the clearneſs and perſpicuity of the contrary duty of peaceableneſs, patient ſuffering, loving their enemies, and the like, it may as readily be concluded, there was ſome inordinate luſt of Domination, Envie, Raſhneſs, Impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, or the like, which they ought to have mortify'd and did not, that led them into this groſs miſtake.</p>
            <p>Upon the whole matter, my Judgement is, That inſtead of inſulting and railing upon them, in Accuſations <hi>which the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119302:4"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 38 -->
would not uſe, when contending with the devil;</hi> Let our hearts melt over them in pity and compaſſion. Let us pray for them that yet remain in the Land of the Living, as our Lord did in a much worſe caſe, <hi>Father, forgive them; for they know not what they do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for our own part, let us lay our Hands upon our Hearts, and diligently conſider, with ſobriety and modeſty, what our Opinions are, in matters of Religion; eſpecially ſuch as are of great concernment to the Honour of God, and our own and others welfare! Let us examine our ſelves by their En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſample! Do we not entertain, and ſeverely hold, and think them juſtly deſerving puniſhment that hold the contrary to ſome Doctrines and Practiſes which perhaps we never took half the pains to ſearch into, nor made a third part of thoſe Prayers to beg direction in, as theſe have done, that are thus miſtaken? Let us not then think, that to kill men by an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Law, or ſtarve them in Priſon, or otherwiſe deſtroy them, (though therein we are perſwaded we do well, as theſe did) are infinitely leſs evil then what they have done. Much leſs let's imagine, that becauſe men are ſometime miſtaken in their Zeal, that therefore it's good to be luke-warm, or to caſt on Religion as a melancholy fancie, and which expoſes men to needleſs Hazards and Self-denials: <hi>Let's not tread the Blood of Chriſt under our feet,</hi> or <hi>count it a common thing,</hi> becauſe of ſome Mens folly, who adore it: Neither let us ſhut our eyes, and give up our ſelves, with the Papiſts, to a blinde Faith and Devotion; and to be led in Religion, as the Governour ſhall pleaſe, becauſe in the following our own Judgements we may miſtake: For, beſides that God loves not theſe <hi>blinde Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices,</hi> he hath commanded us in theſe matters to <hi>call no man Maſter upon earth; for one is our Maſter, even Chriſt:</hi> and all are commanded to <hi>come unto him, and learn of him, who is meek and lowly,</hi> ready to teach us, <hi>upbraiding none.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But further, if we reckon the hainouſneſs of ſin, by the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignity of the will, as we ought, and not by the greatneſs of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119302:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 38 -->
the matter wherein the offence is; what ſhall we ſay of thoſe ſins that are committed wittingly and willingly, in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of this, that's done through a falſe perſwaſion? Shall the killing men in Duels, or in willful Drunkenneſs or heedleſs, Anger, be counted among venial ſins? Shall the defiling the Marriage-Bed, Murthering-falſe-witneſs, and grinding Extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and prophane ſwearing and forſwearing, be deemed ſuch Peccadillo's, being done againſt full knowledge, and with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation? <hi>Shall we think that thoſe upon whom the Tower of Shiloh fell, were greater ſinners then all that were in Jeruſalem?</hi> Chriſt tells us, <hi>Nay, but except we repent, we ſhall all likewiſe periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Methinks this ſad Example gives a ſore che<gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k to the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of late times, wherein men have been and are very rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to place the chief of Religion, if not the whole of it, in ſome Opinion or Practice, (which if it be true and good, is yet of leſſer moment) and in reſpect of that, to neglect or under-value all other parts of Faith and Profeſſion; thus with the Scribes and Phariſees, <hi>tything mint, and aniſe, and cummin;</hi> with <hi>neglect of the weightier matters of the Law, Juſtice, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and Faith.</hi> Is it not an Epidemical Errour, To think that Salvation depends more upon Truth of Judgement, then Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs of Converſation? Whereas it is certain that at Erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious man may be ſaved; but an Unholy man ſhall certainly be damned. Do not many men think God muſt needs accept, their Publike VVorſhip, although they ſeem even to worſhip the Devil at home, by all manner of Prophaneneſs? Do not our Allo-Baptiſts lay a greater ſtreſs upon the point of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm, then any other part of Divine Doctrine, or Holy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation? For ſurely one great evil of theſe men we ſpeak of was. Their over-weening that Doctrine of the Civil Reigne of Chriſt over the Kingdoms of the World, placing as it were, all a Chriſtians Duty, in the promoting thereof. Let us alſo take heed of thoſe affections that might poſſibly have Influence in precipitating them into this Miſchief. Let as beware of ſingularity and prejudice. In Controverſal
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119302:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 39 -->
matters of Concernment, let us keep an Ear for each party, and not eſpouſe one ſide, before we underſtand either: He that ſwallows thoſe Doctrines and Patterns he firſt meets with, it is rather by Chance then Choice, if he light one the Truth. As for the unconſtant and changing perſon, it is to be wiſh'd, he would ſet himſelf to be incorporated and united with ſome one good and profitable Principle; ſo would he not ſuffer ſo much for the future. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> teaches us how to avoid both this Whirle-pool of Levity, and the Quickſand of Prepoſſeſſion, when he bids us, <hi>Try all things, and hold faſt that which is good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your next enquiry is, whether I think this fact of theſe Monarchy-Men may not juſtly reflect ſuch guilt upon the whole Party of thoſe that ſerv'd the remnant of the Long-Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and the Protectors, known by the diſtinctions of Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents, Presbyterians, Anabaptiſts and Quakers, as to make them uncapable of ſome part of that indulgence which is ſhew'd them in the Act of Oblivion, and other his Majeſties Declarations; and the rather, becauſe the Protector in the caſe of an inſurrection againſt his Government, mulct the whole Party? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will ſay little to that Act of the Protector; only I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber it was not then approved even by many of his own Party, as being of dangerous conſequence. But as to this, I do freely give you my judgement, that in equity it cannot be imputed as aforeſaid, and that for theſe Reaſons.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Theſe are the very men that were drawing out into the field in Arms, under there royal ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard in <hi>Olivers</hi> ti<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>Firſt, It's well known that this Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Party have been conſtant Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the whole Party, under both thoſe Denominations, of Commonwealths-Men, and Protectoreans, ever ſince the breaking up of the Little Parliament. Now there is no ſhew of Reaſon, that having been at diſtance ſo long, (though
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119302:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 39 -->
once Friends) that the one ſhould ſuffer for the other, but every one to bear his own burthen.</p>
            <p>Secondly, They are profeſſedly of differing Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, in matters of Government.</p>
            <p>For firſt, They differ with both the ſorts afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named, in that they all hold themſelves obliged to ſubmit to the Government which the Will of GOD ſhall put them under; and the Protecto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reans ſeem to like Monarchy better then another Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. The Commonwealths-Men think the King hath a Commonwealth-Title to the Crown, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing choſen to it by the Unanimous Conſent of the Peoples Repreſentative in Parliament: So that no Prince in the World hath a better Title. But theſe on the contrary (as the Event ſadly manifeſts) thinke themſelves obliged to oppoſe all Government, but that of the Saints, as they call it: and judge the Conſent of the People in general, no Conſent; foraſmuch as Saints onely have Right to Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Governours and Government.</p>
            <p>The Commonwealths-Men could wiſh that all Men were Saints, or at leaſt, that the Saints onely might Govern; But they judge, that till CHRIST come with an Irreſiſtable Power, to give the Government of the World to the Saints, they muſt ſtill follow that Old General Rule,
<q>Do unto Others, as Ye would they ſhould do unto You.</q>
They that are not Politically Unſociable, ſhould
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119302:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 40 -->
not be deprived of Their Share in Civil Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
            <p>Again, Theſe admit of Humane Prudence in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comodating Laws to the Condition, Temper, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, Clymate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the People; and herein would have the Rules of the Jewiſh Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and Chriſtian Precepts to bear ſway as much as conveniently may be; but that in Munici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Laws, God has left men liberty of Creating Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Ordinances, as the State ſhall require. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, leave no ſuch liberty, but would have the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial Laws of the Jewiſh State ſeverely obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, this ſort of men have been as far ingag'd in the ſuppreſſing of the Tumult; and thereby have ſhewn as much diſlike of the Fact, as the reſt of their Neighbours, and as their truſt did per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I have heard, that upon their Examination at Guild-Hall, before the Lieutenant, they have vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated the men I am vindicating, from having any Hand of Conſpiracy, or Correſpondence with them in this matter. Some of them ſaying, There were not one Hundred in all <hi>England</hi> that ever knew of their PLOT, and denying that they had any Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates, either in City or Country, from whom they did, or could expect any Aſſiſtance in their At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:119302:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 40 -->Wherefore ſeeing the caſe is ſo, that the fault can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reaſonably and equitably be charged upon them in any meaſure, I perſwad my ſelf that our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours will give no ſuch Advice, as (if they give this) will make ſufferers more thouſands of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents, then there were Individuals of Nocents, in that ſtrange Enterprize.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
